<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Pedagogy | masondesu]]></title>
  <link href="http://masondesu.github.com/blog/categories/pedagogy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://masondesu.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-18T16:58:14-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://masondesu.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mason Stewart]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ender's Game, Pedagogy, and Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://masondesu.github.com/blog/2014/01/18/enders-game/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-18T15:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://masondesu.github.com/blog/2014/01/18/enders-game</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id='enders_game'>Ender&#8217;s Game</h3>

<p><strong>This post is spoiler free.</strong> Having never read <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/375802.Ender_s_Game'><em>Ender&#8217;s Game</em></a> until two weeks ago, I was thrilled when Katie, my dear wife, surprised me with a copy of the book just before Christmas. She has a wonderful habit of buying books for me that she thinks I&#8217;ll enjoy, even if there&#8217;s no particular occasion.</p>

<p>I expected a fast-paced, satisfying sci-fi novel, and was not disappointed. I realized quickly, however, what had elevated the book to such legendary status. It that was that <em>Ender&#8217;s Game</em> speaks to so many people, across so many ages and ideals, all at once. Politics, war, love, government, science, teaching, learning, duty, religion, nationalism: these weighty topics saturate the novel from start to finish, and each is up for trial. Each topic in turn is shown in a disturbing light, and few have any glimmer of hope or goodness left when the book comes to a close.</p>

<p>Without giving away the plot, it can at least be said that <em>Ender&#8217;s Game</em> is partly about pushing students to the brink. It&#8217;s about dangerously balancing between what happens when they&#8217;re pushed to realize their full potential, and when they&#8217;re pushed too far.</p>
<!-- more -->
<h3 id='the_limits_of_learning'>The Limits of Learning</h3>

<p>As a teacher, it gave me pause. Not so much in the reading, but as I started the new semester and my students were immediately met with very difficult coursework. Images of weary students from the book flashed into my mind as I saw my own tired students dragging into class the next day. The homework had kept many of them up late into the night.</p>

<p>I push my programming students extremely hard. Last semester I pushed my class considerably further into JavaScript than I did with the semester before that. Just before this Winter semester began, I told a number of colleagues and alumni that I had no intention to push much harder than I had before, at least in terms of curriculum. I instead would keep the (very fast) pace mostly the same, and focus on improving the disciplines surrounding the craft of programming, viz. asking them to write about their experiences (a discipline I could certainly stand to improve upon myself!), being even stricter about documentation and testing (when applicable), to speak at meetups, and to read non-JavaScript papers and books and give presentations on them throughout the semester. It is my belief that these disciplines will help each student measure and refine their own growth as programmers.</p>

<p>Even so, the pace and rigor of my class is enough take almost any new programmer to the brink, and I see it a serious duty to carefully, and kindly, guard my students against burnout.</p>

<p>Whether you love or hate the book, it is to me, and likely to many others, a cautionary tale about the extremes of learning and training. And for that, I am thankful.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
